Cooksey-Robertson Family papers, Inclusive: 1859-1981, Bulk: 1862-1864
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Cooksey-Robertson Family papers
Inclusive: 1859-1981, Bulk: 1862-1864
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
3904
Cooksey, A.J.
1 document box.
The Cooksey-Robertson Family papers primarily contain letters from A.J. Cooksey to his family in Montgomery County, Texas, during the American Civil War. Other materials include family birth certificates, transcripts of letters, and tax receipts, and a log book documenting cotton picked that season.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Poor.
Biography/Profile
A.J. Cooksey was born on 1833 July 3 in Alabama. At some point Cooksey moved to Texas, and he married Elizabeth Henson Tubb Cooksey on 1860 February 21 in Montgomery County, Texas. Together they had four children: Luella born 1861 April 17, James Alvis born 1862 December 24, Anne O’Neal born 1867 August 20, and Anner Jackson born 1880 June 25. At the time of the Civil War, the Cooksey family still lived in Montgomery County.
Finding enough men to serve in the Confederate army was a constant problem, and this issue drove the South to pass a draft law in early 1862. While the conscription law certainly brought in new men for the army, many civilians enlisted immediately upon passage of the law so that they could have some choice in the matter, instead of being forced to serve. In this political climate immediately after the conscription law passed, the 20th Texas Infantry was formed in the summer of 1862. A.J. Cooksey joined Company H of the 20th Texas, which was also known as Elmer's Regiment.
Cooksey served for the rest of the war with the 20th Texas, which was assigned to guard the Texas coastline for the duration of the war. For three long years, Cooksey helped patrol the area around Galveston, watching for Union naval activities. His regiment, or perhaps his company, seemed to be based in Oakland, Brazoria County (close to Galveston) for most of the war, as indicated by addresses on his letters. Andrew Jackson Cooksey died on 1880 April 2, three months before the birth of his youngest child.
Other Civil War letters in the collection appear to be from the Robertson family. None are originals, but a transcript of one letter indicates he was in the 7th Texas Infantry, Gregg's Regiment, Granbury's Brigade, Army of the Tennessee.
The Robertson family connection to the Cooksey family is through A.J. Cooksey's son, James Alvis Cooksey. His granddaughter Reba Laucille Rushing married Henry W. Robertson, and the birth certificates for Reba and Henry’s children, as well as other materials from the ancestors of A.J. Cooksey, can be found in the collection.
This collection provides a rich historical look at guarding the Gulf Coast during the American Civil War.
Scope and Content
The Cooksey-Robertson Family papers describes the service of two men in the Confederate army during the American Civil War. Through letters home, these men give a picture of army life, along with advice about how to run the farm back home, regret that they are away from their families, and wishes for more letters from home.
The Cooksey-Robertson Family papers consist of letters, birth certificates, tax receipts, and log books. There is one piece of original Confederate currency in the collection.
The bulk of this collection are the letters A.J. Cooksey wrote home to his wife, Elizabeth Henson Tubb Cooksey. In many of the letters, he refers to her by two nicknames: "Turnip" and "Lizzie." He mentions their daughter Luella (he calls her Lula) frequently as well. Since Cooksey was posted to guard the Texas coast, he does not write about many battles or marching from place to place, but instead describes camp life, news from the battle front, and his instructions to his wife about how to run the farm in his absence. All of these letters are transcribed, and each description is with the original letter in the collection.
Arrangement
Prior this finding aid, the Cooksey-Robertson Family papers were organized loosely with an earlier legacy finding aid. The two series from the first finding aid, though not called series, were preserved.
Currently, the Cooksey-Robertson Family papers are arranged in two series: I. Cooksey Family and II. Robertson Family.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 3904.
Related Resources
Related references
"Civil War: Texas Coast" [vertical file]. The Texas Collection, Baylor University.
Find A Grave, Inc. "Elizabeth Hensen Tubb Cooksey." Memorial #23865191. Databases. Accessed 2014 September 15.
Hathcock, James A. "Twentieth Texas Infantry." Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2014 September 15.
Kleiner, Diana J. "Oakland, TX (Brazoria County)." Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2014 September 15.
The American Civil War Research Database. “Regiment Data: 20th Texas Infantry Regiment (Confederate).” Alexander Street Press, LLC. Accessed 2014 September 15.
The American Civil War Research Database. “Soldier Data: A.J. Cooksey.” Alexander Street Press, LLC. Accessed 2014 September 15.
Index Terms
Places
Gulf Coast (Tex.) -- History.; Montgomery County (Tex.) -- History.; Texas -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.
Subjects
Coast defenses -- Texas.
Genres
Certificates.; Correspondence.
- Cooksey Family, circa 1859-1873; 1
  Administrative Information
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains the letters of A.J. Cooksey to his wife Elizabeth Henson Tubb Cooksey throughout the Civil War. Also included are a log book of cotton picked during a season, and an 1863 tax receipt.
  - Letters from A.J. Cooksey to Elizabeth Henson Tubb Cooksey, 1862 May-September (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters from A.J. Cooksey to Elizabeth Henson Tubb Cooksey, 1862 October-1863 August (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters from A.J. Cooksey to Elizabeth Henson Tubb Cooksey, 1863 September-December (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters from A.J. Cooksey to Elizabeth Henson Tubb Cooksey, 1864 January-March (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters from A.J. Cooksey to Elizabeth Henson Tubb Cooksey, 1864 June-July (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters from A.J. Cooksey to Elizabeth Henson Tubb Cooksey, 1864 August-December (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters from A.J. Cooksey to Elizabeth Henson Tubb Cooksey, 1865-1873 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Copies of Fragments of Letters, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Tax Receipt, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - A.J. Cooksey Cotton Picking Log Book, circa 1859 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Copies of A.J. Cooksey Cotton Picking Log Book, circa 1859 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Robertson Family, 1861-1981; 2
  This series includes documents about the Robertson family, descendants from the A.J. Cooksey family. Several transcripts of Civil War letters and birth, marriage, and death certificates can be found in this series.
  - Letters, William A. Ruyle and R.F. Ellis, 1861, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Birth Certificates, 1941-1953 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Notarized Deposition, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Death Certificates, 1976, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 15)